Register of the Juliene Williams papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Juliene Williams papers
1965-2011
1970-1988
2013C9
Hoover Institution Archives
15 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (7.3 linear feet)
Correspondence, notes, newsletters, printed matter, photographs, memorabilia, and personal documents relating to American prisoners of war and missing in action in the Vietnam War, and to activities of the National League of Families of American Prisoners and Missing in Southeast Asia. Includes the papers of William's first husband, Captain Gordon C. Hill, who was reported missing in action in Laos in 1970.
Williams, Juliene, d. 2011.
Hill, Gordon C.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2012.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Juliene Williams (née Afton Andrews) was the wife of Captain Gordon Clark Hill, a United States Air Force pilot who was reported missing in action (MIA) in Laos in 1970.
Williams was born on July 11, 1946 to Paul J. and Marilyn Andrews in Payson, Utah and attended high schools in Washington, Montana, and Colorado. She graduated from New Mexico State University (NMSU) in 1968. While attending NMSU, Williams met Gordon C. Hill (born October 9,1944), also known as "Bud." They married on January 22, 1966 and together had a son, Brian Ray Hill, born February 4, 1968.
Gordon C. Hill entered the Air Force in May 1967. In 1969, Hill was transferred to the Korat Royal Thai Air Force Base as part of the 469th Tactical Fighter Squadron. On June 30, 1970, Hill and Captain Mitchell O. Sadler, Jr. were declared missing in action (MIA) after their plane failed to meet a refueling tanker during a reconnaissance mission in central Laos. Hill's status was changed from MIA to KIA (killed in action) in 1978.
Shortly after receiving news of her husband's MIA status, Juliene Williams moved to Palo Alto, California and became actively involved with Vietnam prisoner of war (POW) and MIA organizations. She was a member of the National League of Families of American Prisoners and Missing in Southeast Asia and served in leadership roles with the Friends of the POW/MIA League of Santa Clara County.
Juliene Williams married Thomas E. Williams on December 6, 1980, with whom she had a second child, Afton Elizabeth Williams. With Thomas she ran AIW, Inc., a plumbing, hardware, and lighting business in downtown Palo Alto for several years. Juliene Williams died on February 8, 2011.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Juliene Williams papers contain correspondence, notes, newsletters, printed matter, photographs, memorabilia, and personal documents relating to American prisoners of war (POW) and missing in action (MIA) in the Vietnam War, mainly from the years 1970 to 1988. Included are the papers of her first husband, Captain Gordon C. Hill, who was reported MIA in Laos in 1970. The papers document Williams' activities with POW/MIA organizations, such as the National League of Families of American Prisoners and Missing in Southeast Asia, as well as her own efforts to raise awareness of MIA issues and to uncover more information about what happened to her husband.
The Correspondence section contains Williams' personal correspondence with government officials, family, and friends. Much of the correspondence relates to POW/MIA issues and letter writing campaigns against Bo Gritz, a former United States Army Special Forces officer who had conducted a series of private trips to Vietnam in the 1980s to search for live POWs. Correspondence can also be found in the POW/MIA Research File, organized by topic.
The Air Force File contains materials Williams received from the Air Force following Hill's MIA status. This includes her official notification of his status, subsequent updates on his status, mailings sent to all MIA families, and copies of documents from Hill's official case file. It also includes her correspondence with the Air Force requesting more information about her husband's case.
Mailings, correspondence, newsletters, notes, ephemera, and other printed mater related to Williams' involvement with POW/MIA organizations can be found in the Organizations File. It includes material documenting the activities of the National League of Families of American Prisoners and Missing in Southeast Asia, also known as the National League of POW/MIA Families, from 1970 to 2010. It also includes meeting minutes, notes, and other material from the Friends of the POW/MIA League of Santa Clara County, with whom Williams held positions as public relations officer and treasurer. Although the group dissolved in 1974, Williams remained friends with many women from this group, which is documented in the Correspondence series.
Most of the material related directly to Captain Gordon C. Hill can be found in the Gordon C. Hill Biographical File, Oversize Material, and Memorabilia sections. The Biographical File contains some of Hill's personal papers, including his baby book, yearbooks, photographs, and Air Force training records. Military awards and medals Hill received can be found in the Oversize Material and Memorabilia series.
The POW/MIA Research File contains news clippings, correspondence, and notes organized by Williams according to subject. Additional news clippings and articles relating to Vietnam POW/MIA issues and organized by year can be found in the News File. All other printed matter, including periodicals, is located in the Printed Matter section.
Related Collections
Maerose J. Evans papers, Hoover Institution Archives
National League of Families of American Prisoners and Missing in Southeast Asia miscellany, Hoover Institution Archives
Richard A. Stratton papers, Hoover Institution Archives
National League of Families of American Prisoners and Missing in Southeast Asia.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Prisoners and prisons, North Vietnamese.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Missing in action.
- Correspondence, 1970-2009, undated (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains Williams' personal correspondence, mainly with government officials, regarding Vietnam POW/MIA issues. Also included is the collected correspondence of Don Marquart, whom Williams worked with on letter writing campaigns; drafts of letters; and some family correspondence.
  - General, 1970-1973, 1982-1984
    Also includes the collected correspondence of Don Marquart.
    - 1970 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    - 1971 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - 1972 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - 1973 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - 1982 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - 1983 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - 1984 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Addresses, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Andrews family, 2006, undated (Box-folder 1: 9)
    Contains a draft of a letter to Williams' father, as well as printouts of emails between Williams and her two brothers, Greg Andrews and Michael Andrews.
  - Beckstead, Robert W., 1992 August 17 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Christmas cards, 1970-1971, 1996, 2002-2008 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    Contains eight Christmas cards from U.S. presidents, some of which are addressed to Hill and Williams' son, Brian C. Hill. Also included is one card from Robert C. Seamans, Jr., Secretary of the Air Force.
  - Drafts, 1985, undated (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Evans, Maerose, 1971-1974, 1990 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Page, Lou, 1995 January 23 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    General note
    See also: file of the same name in POW/MIA Research File series.
  - Stratton, Alice, 2007, 2009 (Box-folder 1: 15)
    Mainly relates to discussion of a reunion of some of the members of the Friends of the POW/MIA League of Santa Clara County.
- Gordon C. Hill Biographical File, 1945-1978, undated (Boxes 1-3)
  Contains material related to Gordon C. Hill's childhood and time in the Air Force. Includes his baby book, personal documents, photographs, yearbooks, and Air Force training materials.
  - Baby book, 1945-1955 (Box-folder 1: 16)
    Includes childhood photographs of Hill and his family.
  - Diploma, New Mexico State University (NMSU), 1967 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Fishing and hunting licenses, 1960-1964 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Passport application, 1969 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Personal documents, 1963-1970, 1978 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    Contains Hill's passport and a semester report card from NMSU, and documents regarding Hill's posthumous promotion to major and his change in status from MIA to KIA.
  - Photographs, 1967, undated (Box-folder 2: 5)
    Contains Hill's official Air Force portrait, a portrait of Hill getting into an Air Force jet, and two photographs with his mother and Williams taken at his ROTC graduation.
  - Tree dedication ceremony, 1973 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    Contains photographs, programs, and news articles from a tree dedication ceremony held in Mountain View, California on June 30, 1973. The ceremony honored Hill and Major Joseph Bors, who was reported MIA in South Vietnam in 1968.
  - United States Air Force training file, 1967-1970
    Contains certificates, records, progress reports, and other material related to Hill's Air Force training prior to his deployment overseas.
    - 469th Tactical Fighter Squadron, circa 1969 (Box-folder 2: 7)
      Includes Hill's letter of recommendation to the USAF Operational Training Course, as well as a group photograph of the squadron.
    - Assignments, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 2: 8)
    - Flight records, 1967-1970 (Box-folder 2: 9)
    - Jet school, Webb Air Force Base, 1967-1970 (Box-folder 2: 10)
    - Survivors school, Fairchild Air Force Base, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 2: 11)
    - Operational Training Course student folder, 1969 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Yearbooks, 1958, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 2: 13-15, 3: 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1960, 1970-1973, undated (Box-folder 3: 2)
    Contains an application for a Red Cross Safety Instructor course filled out by Hill, correspondence between Hill's parents and Congressman Glenn M. Anderson regarding Hill's MIA status, and a postcard for the Friends of the POW/MIA League of Santa Clara County featuring Hill.
- Air Force File, 1970-1978, 1993-2010 (Boxes 3-5)
  Contains correspondence, official reports, documents from Hill's official Air Force file, and other material Juliene Williams received from the Air Force regarding her husband's MIA status and her efforts to find out more information about what happened to him.
  - Correspondence, 1970-1978, 1984-2010
    - 1970-1978 (Box-folder 3: 3-11)
    - 1984-1985 (Box-folder 3: 12-13)
    - 1988-1994 (Box-folder 3: 14-20)
    - 1995-2010 (Box-folder 4: 1-16)
  - 1994 case review, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 4: 17)
    Contains documents relating to a Department of Defense review of cases of American servicemen and civilians who were unaccounted for during the Vietnam War.
  - 1998 crash site investigation file, 1993-2010 (Box-folder 4: 18-20, 5: 1-2)
    Contains copies of documents, photographs, and correspondence relating to a Joint Task Force investigation of a site in the Phou Kout District of Laos, where a plane was believed to have crashed in mid-1970. Although the task force originally believed the crash site could be related to Hill's disappearance, a direct correlation could not be determined. The first folder includes a CD-R.
  - Accounting, 1971-1973, 1978 (Box-folder 5: 3)
    Contains correspondence and information Williams received from the Air Force regarding Hill's earnings after he was declared MIA.
  - Belasco, Amy, Larry A. Niksch, Lynn J. Cunningham, and Hannah Fischer, Congressional Restrictions on U.S. Military Operations in Vietnam, Cambodia, Laos, Somalia, and Kosovo: Funding and Non-Funding Approaches, 2007 May 7 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Gordon C. Hill case file, 1970-1978, 2010
    - Case file CD-R, 2010 August 20 (Box-folder 5: 5)
      Includes correspondence.
    - Printouts, 1970-1978 (Box-folder 5: 6)
      Contains printouts of documents from Hill's official Air Force file.
  - MIA status, 1970-1978, 1994
    Contains information Williams received regarding Hill's MIA status and his subsequent change in status to KIA.
    - Notification, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 5: 7)
      Includes Information Pamphlet for Families of United States Servicemen Who Are Prisoners of War or Are Missing in Action in Southeast Asia.
    - Review of status, 1970-1978, 1994 (Box-folder 5: 8)
      Includes two microfiche copies of Hill's Air Force personnel record.
    - Change of status, 1978, 1994 (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - Promotions, 1970-1971, 1978 (Box-folder 5: 10)
- Organizations File, 1970-2010 (Boxes 5-9)
  Contains correspondence, agendas, newsletters, and ephemera from the National League of Families of American Prisoners and Missing in Southeast Asia and the Friends of the POW/MIA League of Santa Clara County that Williams collected as a result of her involvement with the organizations.
  - National League of Families of American Prisoners and Missing in Southeast Asia, 1970-2010
    - 1970-1971 (Box-folder 5: 11-12)
    - 1972-1974 (Box-folder 6: 1-3)
    - 1976-1979 (Box-folder 6: 4-7)
    - 1983-1995 (Box-folder 6: 8-12, Box-folder 7: 1-11)
    - 1996-2010 (Box-folder 8: 1-16)
    - "Analysis of the Final Report of the House Select Committee on Missing Persons in Southeast Asia,", 1977 (Box-folder 8: 17)
    - Eastern Washington chapter, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - Friends of the POW/MIA League of Santa Clara County, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 9: 2-4)
    Includes meeting notes, correspondence, and newsletters generated by the group, which was active from 1971 to 1974. Williams served as an active member of the group, acting as a public relations officer and later as treasurer. Arranged by year. See also: Evans, Maerose; Page, Lou; and Stratton Alice files in the Correspondence series.
- POW/MIA Research File, 1970-2011 (Boxes 9-13)
  Contains correspondence, clippings, newsletters, notes, and other printed matter related to POW/MIA issues and organized by Williams according to subject. Arranged alphabetically according to Williams' original folder titles.
  - ACTION/VISTA [Volunteers in Service to America], 1984 (Box-folder 9: 5)
    ACTION was a federal domestic volunteer agency that was active from 1971 to 1994. VISTA was one of several volunteer programs transferred to ACTION after it was established.
  - Bamboo Connection: A Rambo Faction Publication, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 9: 6)
  - Barnes, Scott, 2004 (Box-folder 9: 7)
  - Childress, Richard T. and Stephen J. Solarz, "Vietnam: Detours on the Road to Restoring Normal Relations,", circa 1995 (Box-folder 9: 8)
  - Central Intelligence Agency, 2006-2010 (Box-folder 9: 9)
  - Department of Defense, 1970-1971, 1983-2011 (Box-folder 9: 10-11)
    Includes news releases, the Next-of-Kin Newsletter, the POW/MIA Newsletter, and correspondence. Also included are issues of the POW-MIA Fact Book from August 1986 and July 1988.
  - DNA registry, 1995, undated (Box-folder 9: 12)
  - Franklin, H. Bruce, "The POW/MIA Myth: How the White House and Hollywood Combined to Foster a National Fantasy,", 1991 (Box-folder 9: 13)
  - Freedom of Information Act, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 9: 14)
  - Geneva Convention violations flyer, 1970 (Box-folder 9: 15)
  - Gritz, James "Bo,", 1981-2009, undated
    Contains newspaper clippings, articles, correspondence, and other material related to James "Bo" Gritz, a former United States Army Special Forces officer who gained fame in the 1980s for taking a series of private trips to Vietnam, where he claimed to have recovered the remains of American soldiers killed during the Vietnam War. Much of the material pertains to a controversy surrounding how Gritz funded these trips and letters Williams and Don Marquart wrote to various people criticizing Gritz and his refusal to turn over the remains to the authorities for examination. Organized by year and then topic according to Williams' original folder titles.
    - 1981 (Box-folder 10: 1)
    - 1982 (Box-folder 10: 2)
    - 1983 (Box-folder 10: 3-6)
    - 1984-1985 (Box-folder 10: 7)
    - 1987 (Box-folder 10: 8)
    - 1988 (Box-folder 10: 9)
    - 1990 (Box-folder 10: 10)
    - 1992 (Box-folder 10: 11)
    - 1998 (Box-folder 10: 12)
    - 2009 (Box-folder 10: 13)
    - 1995 lawsuit, 1982-1983, 1995 (Box-folder 10: 14)
      Contains correspondence, reproductions of documents, and an audio cassette produced by Bo Gritz titled "Maybe Tomorrow" that were provided by Williams for use in a defamation case involving Gritz. Also includes a copy of New Information on U.S. MIA-POW's in Indochina?: Hearing Before the Subcommittee on Asian and Pacific Affairs of the Committee on Foreign Affairs that features testimony by Gritz.
    - Anderson, Jack, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 10: 15)
      Contains articles about Gritz written by Anderson, a journalist for The San Francisco Chronicle. Also includes a draft of a letter written by Williams.
    - Congressional bill, 1984 (Box-folder 11: 1)
      Contains correspondence and news clippings regarding a Congressional bill that would allow the Department of Defense to confiscate alleged remains of servicemen for examination.
    - Federal charges, 1988, 2004 (Box-folder 11: 2)
    - Fund raising, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 11: 3)
    - LA Times notes, undated (Box-folder 11: 4)
    - Tax information, 1982-1984 (Box-folder 11: 5)
    - Van Atta, Michael, 1988 (Box-folder 11: 6)
      Contains correspondence and articles written about Bo Gritz sent to Williams from Michael Van Atta, author of The Insiders newsletter (one copy of the newsletter is included). See also: The Insiders file later in this series.
  - Hayden [Tom] and Fonda [Jane], 1985-1990 (Box-folder 11: 7-8)
  - House Task Force on American Prisoners and Missing in Southeast Asia, 1984 August 7 (Box-folder 11: 9)
    Contains a statement regarding the Task Force's findings on William Hendon's allegations that there was a government cover-up pertaining to live POWs in Southeast Asia.
  - Khmer Rouge, 2008-2009 (Box-folder 11: 10)
  - The Insiders, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 11: 11-13)
    The Insiders was a publication produced by Michael Van Atta. It was first published in 1982 with the aim of informing the American public of "the proof that live POWs are still being held in Southeast Asia" and securing their release.
  - Lantos, Tom, 1985, 2007 (Box-folder 11: 14)
  - Laos, 2009, 2011, undated (Box-folder 11: 15)
  - Laotian coup, 2007 (Box-folder 11: 16)
  - McCain, John, 1988, 2011 (Box-folder 11: 17)
  - MIA identification, 1983, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 11: 18)
  - MIA lawsuit, 1973 (Box-folder 11: 19)
  - Miscellaneous POW/MIA newsletters, 1970 (Box-folder 12: 1)
  - Miscellaneous POW/MIA newsletters, 1972, 1988 (Box-folder 12: 2)
  - Notebooks, 1994, 2008-2011
    Contains various handwritten notes relating to MIA issues and organizations. Also included are some printouts of online articles that were originally found between the pages of the notebooks.
    - 1994 (Box-folder 12: 3)
    - circa 2008 (Box-folder 12: 4)
    - 2010 (Box-folder 12: 5)
    - 2010-2011 (Box-folder 12: 6)
  - Notes, 1983-1994
    Contains loose handwritten notes, mainly related to MIA news and James "Bo" Gritz.
    - 1983-1984 (Box-folder 12: 7)
    - 1983-1987 (Box-folder 12: 8)
    - 1989-1994 (Box-folder 12: 9)
  - Operation Rescue, 1983 (Box-folder 12: 10)
  - Page, Lou, 1998 (Box-folder 12: 11)
    See also: file of the same name in Correspondence series.
  - Pentagon Papers, 1971 (Box-folder 12: 12)
    Contains news clippings related to the publishing of what were dubbed the "Pentagon Papers" by The New York Times. The papers, formally titled United States – Vietnam Relations, 1945–1967: A Study Prepared by the Department of Defense, were released by Daniel Ellsberg in 1971.
  - Perot, Ross, 1983, 1987 (Box-folder 12: 13)
  - Photograph with Congressman Ed Zschau, undated (Box-folder 12: 14)
  - POW/MIA pamphlets and bumper stickers, undated (Box-folder 12: 15)
  - Roger Hall lawsuit, 2007 (Box-folder 12: 16)
    Contains copies of an email containing a court case file from Roger Hall, et al. v. Central Intelligence Agency.
  - Reestablishment of trade with Vietnam, 1988, 2003 (Box-folder 12: 17)
  - Remains identification, 1985 (Box-folder 12: 18)
  - Schanberg, Sydney, 2011 (Box-folder 12: 19)
  - Scowcroft, Brent, 1973, 2005-2006 (Box-folder 12: 20)
  - Senate Select Committee, 1993 January 3 (Box-folder 12: 21)
  - Southern Texas POW/MIA newsletter, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 12: 22)
  - Stolz, Larry, 2009 (Box-folder 12: 23)
  - Task Force Omega, 1983 (Box-folder 12: 24)
  - United States Senate, 1995 July 20 (Box-folder 12: 25)
  - Unknown Soldier - Vietnam, 1984 (Box-folder 12: 26)
  - Vietnam, 2006 (Box-folder 12: 27)
  - Vietnam Veterans of America, 1987 (Box-folder 12: 28)
  - Virtual JFK: Vietnam if Kennedy Had Lived, 2009 (Box-folder 12: 29)
    Contains articles and clippings about the documentary film that speculates how John F. Kennedy might have handled Vietnam if he had not been assassinated.
  - Voices in Vital America (VIVA), 1971-1973 (Box-folder 12: 30)
    Contains mailings and correspondence regarding permission to use Captain Hill's name on one of VIVA's POW/MIA bracelets. Also included is VIVA's 1972 annual report and a letter addressed to Williams from someone who wore Hill's MIA bracelet.
  - The Wall, undated (Box-folder 13: 1)
    Contains two rubbings and a photograph of Hill's name from the Vietnam Veterans Memorial Wall in Washington D.C.
  - Miscellany, 1983-1994, 2006-2010, undated (Box-folder 13: 2)
    Contains materials from an unlabeled file. Includes a group photograph of unidentified men, a printout of the article "National Security Archive Publishes Digitized Set of 2,100 Henry Kissinger 'Memcons' Recounting the Secret Diplomacy of the Nixon-Ford Era," and ephemera.
- News File, 1970-2010, undated (Boxes 13-15)
  Contains news clippings and printouts of online news articles related to POW/MIA news, Laos, and Vietnam. These files were arranged chronologically by Williams.
  - 1970 (Box-folder 13: 3)
  - 1970-1971, undated (Box-folder 13: 4)
  - 1971 (Box-folder 13: 5-7)
  - 1972 (Box-folder 13: 8)
  - 1973 (Box-folder 13: 9)
  - 1979 (Box-folder 13: 10)
  - 1980 (Box-folder 13: 11)
  - 1983 (Box-folder 13: 12)
  - 1984 (Box-folder 13: 13)
  - 1985-2000 (Box-folder 14: 1-16)
  - 2002-2007 (Box-folder 14: 17-22)
  - 2009-2010 (Box-folder 15: 1-2)
- Printed Matter, 1970-1971, 1984-1986 (Box 15)
  Contains periodicals and pamphlets related to Vietnam POWs and MIAs.
  - The Geneva Convention Relative to the Treatment of Prisoners of War. With Reservations, if Any, by Governments Participating in Hostilities in Vietnam, Cambodia and Laos, 1970 May (Box-folder 15: 3)
  - House Concurrent Resolution 322, 98th Congress, 1984 June 19 (Box-folder 15: 4)
  - Periodicals, 1970-1971, 1986
    - Air Force and Space Digest, 1970 June (Box-folder 15: 5)
    - Airman, 1971 January (Box-folder 15: 6)
    - Commanders Digest, Department of Defense, 1970 (Box-folder 15: 7)
      Contains issues from June 13, July 11, and October 17, 1970.
    - Congressional Record: Proceedings and Debates of the 91st Congress, Second Session, 1970 (Box-folder 15: 8)
      Contains numbers 90, 91, and 165.